<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
     <title> Wikipaulia </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#</link>
     <description> An epidemiologist dabbles in statistics, coding, open source software and the cloud. </description>
     <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 15:22:57 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
     <title> 2023-06-24 Xerte Online Toolkits; k-anonymisation; polars; j'accuse le tidyverse; DHIS 2 API; getting yak shaving done </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2023-06-24%20Xerte%20Online%20Toolkits%3B%20k-anonymisation%3B%20polars%3B%20j%27accuse%20le%20tidyverse%3B%20DHIS%202%20API%3B%20getting%20yak%20shaving%20done</link>
     <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 13:44:46 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>- Busy busy; two foreign trips in a short space of time and other pressing deadlines, so not much blogging recently - but made up for it these last weekends - I now have my own installation of the wonderful [Xerte Online Toolkits](&lt;#Installing Xerte Online Toolkits on Ubuntu 22.04 Linux &gt;) for e-learning, which is [easy to embed](&lt;#Embedding Xerte Online Toolkits e-learning in a Web page - example &gt;) in other Web sites - also worked out [how to tweak XOT behaviour with JQuery](&lt;#Xerte Online Toolkits: hiding the Next button for a specified time &gt;) - Wrote up my experience of [anonymising data with the <code>sdcMicro</code> Shiny app](&lt;#k-anonymising data sets with the sdcMicro Shiny app &gt;) - Thought I had found [something faster than <code>data.table</code>](&lt;#Is polars faster than data.table? &gt;) for R coding - Have started to learn the tidyverse but [needed to get some "bah humbug" out of my system](&lt;#Adapt or perish: learning the tidyverse&gt;) first - Did an [introductory article on the DHIS 2 Web API](&lt;#The DHIS 2 API - part 1 &gt;) for getting data out of DHIS 2 - Wrote a reflective note on [my approach to productivity](&lt;#Getting Things Done, the todo.txt format and the quest for the perfect productivity system &gt;), then stayed up very late over-engineering [a replacement system](&lt;#Fun with file formats: todo.txt and the iCalendar format &gt;)</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2023-03-29 Blog makeover; code-switching (R &amp; Python); field epidemiology toolkit; our new AI overlords </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2023-03-29%20Blog%20makeover%3B%20code-switching%20%28R%20%26%20Python%29%3B%20field%20epidemiology%20toolkit%3B%20our%20new%20AI%20overlords</link>
     <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 08:09:17 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>- Updated the blog with [a new theme](&lt;#New Tiddlywiki theme: Captivate Theme&gt;), instead of getting a haircut; I like my new online presence anyway, and no one sees the physical me very much these days - Was pleasantly surprised by how much affection I still have for Python, and how easy the <code>reticulate</code> package makes [combining R with Python](&lt;#Combining R and Python in RStudio&gt;) - Newly dumped into the blog: the text of a [field epidemiology toolkit](&lt;#Field Epidemiology Toolkit&gt;) document I wrote most of years ago, just so that is there somewhere (NB: some of it is a bit dated, written at a time when epidemiologists were still a bit sniffy about online questionnaires, and used neolithic tools like EpiData) - A lot of my non-meeting time has been filled with meetings recently so I haven't done any exciting global health informatics things, but I did join a [good webinar on getting data into DHIS 2 by SMS](&lt;#Webinar on RapidPro-DHIS2 integration&gt;) and while doing some routine maintenance on my demo versions [I managed to accidentally send some of my tweaks to the developers](&lt;#In which I accidentally submit a pull request to Ozone HIS&gt;) - Embedded a couple of cool things I like looking at into the blog: [your local weather forecast](&lt;#Command line weather forecast&gt;) and [a literary clock](&lt;#And the time is...&gt;) - all someone else's cool work - Still [playing around with ChatGPT](&lt;#More fun with ChatGPT&gt;) and [all the shiny new AI tools](&lt;#Things you can now do with AI online&gt;) - Am finally realising I might need to learn the tidyverse if I am going to stay involved in teaching R...</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2023-02-27 Holiday reading; learning R; most frequently bookmarked </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2023-02-27%20Holiday%20reading%3B%20learning%20R%3B%20most%20frequently%20bookmarked</link>
     <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 14:11:57 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>- Yet another holiday (still using up leave carried over from the pandemic) and time to read [more books](#Books). But too soon going back to the *anomie* of the public health world. - Gathered my thoughts on [how to learn R](&lt;#How to learn R (an opinionated view)&gt;). I've recently been accused of "forcing" trainees to learn R. That's just not true - I'd be just as happy if they learned Python. - I collate my public bookmarks on [Pinboard](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://pinboard.in/u:prcleary" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://pinboard.in/u:prcleary</a>). The tagging system is currently a mess, which I need to sort out (and yes, [there's an R package for that](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://github.com/RMHogervorst/pinboardr" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://github.com/RMHogervorst/pinboardr</a>)), but I have done a quick summary of [the sites I tend to bookmark most frequently](&lt;#Most frequently bookmarked&gt;) as a metric of utility. </p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2023-01-19 Informatics book review; LIMS evaluation; information security self-assessment </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2023-01-19%20Informatics%20book%20review%3B%20LIMS%20evaluation%3B%20information%20security%20self-assessment</link>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 22:49:27 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>- Finished an excellent book on public health informatics while on holiday in Mumbai and Rajasthan; as an entirely unqualified IT hobbyist it was good to see I have done some things right, but I also learned a lot about successful implementation of informatics projects in low and middle-income countries; my notes and reflections on the book are [here](&lt;#Public Health Informatics by Sahay et al - notes and reflections&gt;). - Now that I am fairly happy with [my Proxmox data centre implementation](&lt;#Next steps with Proxmox&gt;) I have been extensively [evaluating OpenELIS and SENAITE](&lt;#OpenELIS versus SENAITE as LIMS options&gt;) for open source laboratory information management; finding some pain points in both options but I think SENAITE is our best option; currently finding my way around the [OpenMRS](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://openmrs.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://openmrs.org/</a>) electronic health record platform and will post on that in due course. But this is all looking increasingly unlike a one-man job... - Am putting out there my personal [information security checklist](&lt;#Information Security Self-Assessment&gt;) in case useful to others. Most countries are a long way from achieving this.</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2022-12-04 My own data centre to build a sustainable open source information architecture; Firth's logistic regression; miscellaneous links </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2022-12-04%20My%20own%20data%20centre%20to%20build%20a%20sustainable%20open%20source%20information%20architecture%3B%20Firth%27s%20logistic%20regression%3B%20miscellaneous%20links</link>
     <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 16:38:32 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<ul><li>Had some time recently to think about how all the various open source technologies that are spinning in my head might fit together into an integrated whole; building a <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Open%20source%20e-IDSR%20system%20architecture%20diagram">diagram</a> was very helpful with this and to motivate the conversations that I will need to have; also as my learning has been very much based on experimentation so far I have also <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Proxmox%3A%20your%20own%20data%20centre">set up my own data centre</a> (sort of) to play with the big boys' toys. </li><li>Am trying to put any advice I give on statistical or technical matters straight into the blog; although I was aware of <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Notes%20on%20Firth%27s%20logistic%20regression%20and%20model%20selection">Firth's logistic regression</a> as a method to try if all else failed, from my recent reading it looks like we should consider it more often. </li><li>Some miscellaneous links or notes: <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#DHIS%202%20version%203.9%20-%20wow">the latest DHIS 2</a>, a <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Machine%20Learning%20and%20Deep%20Learning%20-%20A%20review%20for%20Ecologists%20%28arXiv%29">really good article on machine learning and deep learning</a> and some lists of cool tools <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Online%20tools%20which%20may%20occasionally%20be%20useful">here</a>, <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Online%20diagram%20editors">here</a> and <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Useful%20websites%20for%20checking%20if%20your%20site%20is%20secure">here</a>.</li></ul>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2022-11-19 OpenELIS and open source LIMS; Bayesian statistics articles; cool TiddlyWiki plugins </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2022-11-19%20OpenELIS%20and%20open%20source%20LIMS%3B%20Bayesian%20statistics%20articles%3B%20cool%20TiddlyWiki%20plugins</link>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 16:41:56 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<ul><li>Busy couple of weeks with lots to do at work and lots of other stuff going on too</li><li>Set up an instance of OpenELIS (incomplete notes <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#First%20steps%20with%20setting%20up%20demonstration%20versions%20of%20open%20source%20software%20platforms%20in%20the%20cloud">here</a>, aiming to take you right from the beginning of the process of setting up an online Web service securely); also my thoughts on <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Evaluating%20laboratory%20information%20management%20systems%20for%20low%20and%20middle%20income%20countries">criteria for evaluating open source laboratory information systems</a></li><li>Assembled various <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Interested%20in%20Bayesian%20statistics%20and%20want%20to%20know%20more%3F">interesting Bayesian statistics articles</a> following my talk which seemed to go OK; makes you look at <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Use%20of%20Straighteners%20and%20Other%20Hair%20Products%20and%20Incident%20Uterine%20Cancer%20%28open%20access%29">this kind of study</a> rather sceptically</li><li>Discovered more cool things you can do with TiddlyWiki, like including <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Add%20interactive%20charts%20to%20your%20TiddlyWiki">charts</a> and <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Mermaid.js%2C%20a%20Markdown-friendly%20diagram%20tool">diagrams</a></li></ul>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2022-11-08 Python; cheatsheets for R and Git; Bayesian statistics teaching </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2022-11-08%20Python%3B%20cheatsheets%20for%20R%20and%20Git%3B%20Bayesian%20statistics%20teaching</link>
     <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 09:00:58 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<ul><li>Starting to teach my son Python again - we haven't been good at keeping this up previously (and they seem to do very little at school) but I will keep my notes <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Gentle%20introduction%20to%20Python">here</a>. Summarised my thoughts on R/Python bilingualism, as expressed to a colleague, <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Should%20I%20learn%20Python%20now%20I%20know%20R%3F">here</a>. </li><li>Back to doing some coding, this time on TB epidemiology, and collating snippets of R code as I go along, as I usually end up Googling the same things time after time. Creating my own <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#My%20R%20cheatsheet">R cheatsheet</a> for quick things and <span class="tc-tag-list-item" data-tag-title="snippet"><span aria-expanded="false" class="tc-tag-label tc-btn-invisible" draggable="true" style="background-color:#7776ff; fill:#111733; color:#111733;"><svg class="tc-image-code tc-image-button" height="22pt" viewBox="0 0 640 512" width="22pt"><path d="M278.9 511.5l-61-17.7c-6.4-1.8-10-8.5-8.2-14.9L346.2 8.7c1.8-6.4 8.5-10 14.9-8.2l61 17.7c6.4 1.8 10 8.5 8.2 14.9L293.8 503.3c-1.9 6.4-8.5 10.1-14.9 8.2zm-114-112.2l43.5-46.4c4.6-4.9 4.3-12.7-.8-17.2L117 256l90.6-79.7c5.1-4.5 5.5-12.3.8-17.2l-43.5-46.4c-4.5-4.8-12.1-5.1-17-.5L3.8 247.2c-5.1 4.7-5.1 12.8 0 17.5l144.1 135.1c4.9 4.6 12.5 4.4 17-.5zm327.2.6l144.1-135.1c5.1-4.7 5.1-12.8 0-17.5L492.1 112.1c-4.8-4.5-12.4-4.3-17 .5L431.6 159c-4.6 4.9-4.3 12.7.8 17.2L523 256l-90.6 79.7c-5.1 4.5-5.5 12.3-.8 17.2l43.5 46.4c4.5 4.9 12.1 5.1 17 .6z"></path></svg>snippet</span><span class="tc-drop-down tc-reveal" hidden="true"></span></span>s for anything a bit more complicated like a useful function. Also creating <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#My%20Git%20cheatsheet">my own cheatsheet for Git</a>. </li><li>Lecturing on Bayesian statistics soon - my <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Teaching%20Bayesian%20statistics">very rough notes</a> are online. </li></ul>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2022-10-29 Windows Subsystem for Linux 2; Observables; additions to the wiki; what I'm reading </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2022-10-29%20Windows%20Subsystem%20for%20Linux%202%3B%20Observables%3B%20additions%20to%20the%20wiki%3B%20what%20I%27m%20reading</link>
     <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 20:39:08 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<ul><li>As someone who used Linux exclusively for years, and now has to use Windows mainly for work, I am interested in any possible "best of both worlds" solution. Windows Subsystem for Linux (now on version 2) allows you to install one of several versions of Linux alongside Windows. I <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-missing" href="#%20Getting%20Windows%20Subsystem%20for%20Linux%20to%20work%20on%20Windows%20laptops">previously looked at WS1</a> and was a bit disappointed. I <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Windows%20Subsystem%20for%20Linux%20%28WSL2%29%2C%20RStudio%2C%20Git%2C%20Docker%20and%20a%20Windows%20laptop">played around with WSL2</a> this afternoon and it seems to have a lot more potential. It would still be easier to use Linux alone, but WSL2 could be a really useful adjunct for analytical or development work. You can use the Linux command line from RStudio, or run RStudio from Linux. I even managed to get Podman containers working after a bit of experimentation. </li><li>Started to <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#First%20steps%20with%20Observables%20in%20Quarto">see what you can do with Observables</a> in Quarto earlier this week - not sure how much use it is going to be for me, and it seemed like a lot of work to get a simple bar chart, but it seems to be very capable in the right hands - see the <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://observablehq.com/@mbostock/tadpoles" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">tadpoles</a> example (are they really tadpoles?)</li><li>In spare moments I have been copying over notes from other places where I have been keeping notes. Most of it is already Markdown and easy to move over, but I also have extensive Vim Outliner notes from a previous period, and also even some Evernote stuff from way back, which I will need to sort out at some point. I am tagging it all <span class="tc-tag-list-item" data-tag-title="stuff"><span aria-expanded="false" class="tc-tag-label tc-btn-invisible" draggable="true" style="background-color:#d3d3d3; fill:#111733; color:#111733;"><svg class="tc-image-seedling tc-image-button" height="22pt" viewBox="0 0 512 512" width="22pt"><path d="M64 96H0c0 123.7 100.3 224 224 224v144c0 8.8 7.2 16 16 16h32c8.8 0 16-7.2 16-16V320C288 196.3 187.7 96 64 96zm384-64c-84.2 0-157.4 46.5-195.7 115.2 27.7 30.2 48.2 66.9 59 107.6C424 243.1 512 147.9 512 32h-64z"></path></svg>stuff</span><span class="tc-drop-down tc-reveal" hidden="true"></span></span> for the moment; bits of code are tagged <span class="tc-tag-list-item" data-tag-title="snippet"><span aria-expanded="false" class="tc-tag-label tc-btn-invisible" draggable="true" style="background-color:#7776ff; fill:#111733; color:#111733;"><svg class="tc-image-code tc-image-button" height="22pt" viewBox="0 0 640 512" width="22pt"><path d="M278.9 511.5l-61-17.7c-6.4-1.8-10-8.5-8.2-14.9L346.2 8.7c1.8-6.4 8.5-10 14.9-8.2l61 17.7c6.4 1.8 10 8.5 8.2 14.9L293.8 503.3c-1.9 6.4-8.5 10.1-14.9 8.2zm-114-112.2l43.5-46.4c4.6-4.9 4.3-12.7-.8-17.2L117 256l90.6-79.7c5.1-4.5 5.5-12.3.8-17.2l-43.5-46.4c-4.5-4.8-12.1-5.1-17-.5L3.8 247.2c-5.1 4.7-5.1 12.8 0 17.5l144.1 135.1c4.9 4.6 12.5 4.4 17-.5zm327.2.6l144.1-135.1c5.1-4.7 5.1-12.8 0-17.5L492.1 112.1c-4.8-4.5-12.4-4.3-17 .5L431.6 159c-4.6 4.9-4.3 12.7.8 17.2L523 256l-90.6 79.7c-5.1 4.5-5.5 12.3-.8 17.2l43.5 46.4c4.5 4.9 12.1 5.1 17 .6z"></path></svg>snippet</span><span class="tc-drop-down tc-reveal" hidden="true"></span></span>. So this is partly blog, partly wiki and partly <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://nesslabs.com/digital-garden-set-up" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">digital garden</a> at the moment.</li><li>See the <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Books">Books</a> page for what I'm currently reading. </li></ul>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> 2022-10-24 Blogging in Tiddlywiki </title>
     <link>https://prcleary.github.io/#2022-10-24%20Blogging%20in%20Tiddlywiki</link>
     <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 18:59:45 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>[TiddlyWiki](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://groktiddlywiki.com/read/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://groktiddlywiki.com/read/</a>), a single page HTML wiki, has been around for a long time. I have used it a lot over the years, first as a single file saved to my computer/USB drive and later as a (now quite large) self-hosted Docker container running behind [CapRover](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://lowendbox.com/blog/install-200-apps-in-your-vps-with-one-click-introduction-to-caprover/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://lowendbox.com/blog/install-200-apps-in-your-vps-with-one-click-introduction-to-caprover/</a>). A TiddlyWiki is a great place to dump anything from random thoughts to checklists to code snippets. You can use [Markdown](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet</a>), plain text, HTML or Tiddlywiki's own wiki syntax to create entries like this one (called "tiddlers"). </p><p>I've just started to get interested in blogging as a way to share niche things that may be of interest to people working in a similar area to me. I have considered or tried out several blogging platforms including [Ghost](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://ghost.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://ghost.org/</a>), [Hugo ](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0RKpf3rK57I" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0RKpf3rK57I</a>) and [Nikola](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://getnikola.com/getting-started.html#installLinux" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://getnikola.com/getting-started.html#installLinux</a>), and of course Wordpress, but wanted something a bit quicker to set up and use. </p><p>Then I came across [this tip on how to use TiddlyWiki as your blog on GitHub](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://pesho-ivanov.github.io/#Two-click%20TiddlyWiki%20with%20GitHub-pages" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://pesho-ivanov.github.io/#Two-click%20TiddlyWiki%20with%20GitHub-pages</a>). As I was already familiar with TiddlyWiki, it took me less than an hour to set this up. </p><p>Couple of notes to future self:</p><p>- I used [Stroll](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://giffmex.org/stroll/stroll.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://giffmex.org/stroll/stroll.html</a>) as my empty <code>index.html</code> file - this is just a souped-up version of TiddlyWiki. - I used a [classic GitHub personal access token](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/keeping-your-account-and-data-secure/creating-a-personal-access-token" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/keeping-your-account-and-data-secure/creating-a-personal-access-token</a>), non-expiring but only with scope <code>public_repo</code>. </p><p>Now I can edit this blog in my browser from anywhere. Tagging is really easy. I don't have to build a whole website to check everything is working. If I keep things simple (i.e. avoid uploading too many attachments or images) this should work well. I still need to work out how to set up an [RSS feed](<a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://kevincox.ca/2022/05/06/rss-feed-best-practices/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">https://kevincox.ca/2022/05/06/rss-feed-best-practices/</a>) but that can come later. </p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
